<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/teibp.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xslt/teibp.xsl"?>
<!--Change xml:id in TEI root to reflect the proper I Witness issue-->
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 iwitness.xsd"
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="VAA7662-001-1">
 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The I Witness</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Rose Jones </name>


                    <orgName> Digital Library Program, Indiana University </orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Digital Library Program, Indiana University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                <date>2009</date>
                <availability status="unknown">
                    <p>Copyright 2009 Trustees of Indiana University</p>
                    <p>Indiana University provides the information contained on this web site for
                        non-commercial, personal, or research use only. All other use, including but
                        not limited to commercial or scholarly reproductions, redistribution,
                        publication or transmission, whether by electronic means or otherwise,
                        without prior written permission of the copyright holder is strictly
                        prohibited.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">The I Witness</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="s">The I Witness</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Indiana University Law School Alumni Association</publisher>
                            <date>1959</date>

                            <biblScope type="issue" n="#">May </biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="volume" n="#">Vol.I, No. 1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pages" n="#">1-6</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl n="4">
                <p>This electronic text file was created by Optical Character Recognition (OCR), and
                    has been encoded and edited using the recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in
                    Libraries Guidelines for Best Encoding Practices. Digital facsimiles are also
                    provided. </p>
                <p>The following features will not be encoded though they are present in the printed
                    text: page breaks, column breaks and article continuations. The latter two do
                    not require faithful representation since facsimiles are provided, and article
                    continuations and column breaks are disruptive to online reading. The page
                    breaks are ommitted since they are complicated by article continuations. The
                    newsletter is no more than a 4-8 pages long so we'll be providing facsimile
                    acess starting on page 1 and from figures contained within the text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The Maurer School of Law, Indiana University, Bloomington, is providing online
                    access to its alumni newsletter, The I Witness, published from 1959-1968, which
                    presents news stories about the law school, its faculty and alumni. .</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">The I-Witness contains primarily English-language
                    content.</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>

            <div type="masthead">

                <bibl>
                    <publisher>Indiana University Law School Alumni Association</publisher>. 
                        <title>The I Witness</title>. 
                    <biblScope type="vol" n="#">1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue" n="#">May</biblScope>
                    <date>1959</date>. <pubPlace>Bloomington, Indiana</pubPlace>. </bibl>
                <p>Published by the Alumni Association of the School of Law of Indiana University.
                    Inquiries should be addressed to the Editor, G17 Union Building, Bloomington,
                    Indiana.</p>
            </div>

        </front>
        <body>


            <div type="editorialMaterial">
                <head>A Message From Dean <persName>Wallace</persName></head>
                <opener>To the Alumni of Indiana University School of Law: </opener>
                <p>It is a pleasure to greet all of you in this first issue of the news bulletin,
                    The I-Witness, sponsored by the Alumni Association of the Law School. Both
                    Divisions of the school continue their successful operation, and when any of you
                    are either in Indianapolis or Bloomington, we hope that you will take time to
                    visit us so that we may have the opportunity of renewing old acquaintance. It is
                    our sincere desire by this publication to keep you in closer touch with Indiana
                    University, and its School of Law. With warmest regards to all of you, I am</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Sincerely yours,</salute> <signed>LEON H. WALLACE <lb/> Dean </signed>
                </closer>


            </div>


            <div type="editorialMaterial">
                <head>EDITORIAL</head>
                <p> Greetings! This issue launches The I-Witness on what we hope will be a long and
                    successful career of service to our alumni. It is designed to keep you abreast
                    of the news concerning your classmates and friends in the Law School, and to
                    supply information about the current activities, development and progress of the
                    School itself.</p>
                <p> We plan to tell you about everything of interest that is happening in both the
                    Bloomington and Indianapolis Divisions, including details of the serious and
                    important work being done, and also some accounts of the lighter moments which
                    relieve the tensions of constant study.</p>
                <p>It is our aim to include an abundance of news concerning our alumni-their present
                    whereabouts, jobs, political offices, types of work they are doing, and even
                    their thoughts about the proper function of the Law School and the needs and
                    interests of the legal profession.</p>
                <p> For this we must depend upon you- send the news concerning yourself or your
                    reticent friends to Mr. <persName>Richard Quaintance</persName>, Assistant Dean,
                    School of Law, <placeName>Bloomington, Indiana</placeName>, for future issues.</p>
                <p> Suggestions for improvement of the contents or format of the paper will be
                    welcomed heartily. </p>
            </div>


            <div type="article">
                <head>School Of Law Alumni Banquet Honoring <persName>John S. Hastings</persName> To
                    Be Held June 7; Alumni, Wives Urged To Attend</head>
                <p>The annual School of Law Alumni reception and banquet will be held on Sunday
                    afternoon,June 7, 1959 in Alumni Hall. The reception will begin at 4:30, the
                    banquet at 5:30. The cost of the dinner will be $3.00 per person and wives are
                    cordially invited. Reservation forms will be sent out by the Alumni Association.
                    Ample housing facilities will be available.</p>
                <p>The program will honor Judge <persName>John S. Hastings</persName>, '24, retiring
                    presirent of the I.U. Board of Trustees. Mr.<persName>Willis Hickam </persName>
                    '18 will deliver the principal address and the portrait of Judge
                        <persName>Hastings</persName>, a gift of the alumni to the law school, will
                    be unveiled.</p>
                <p>As in prior years the graduating seniors will be honored guests. In addition
                    several classes are planning reunions and special tables are being reserved for
                    those classes. Class members are asked to contact the following chairmen
                    concerning reunion plans. 
                </p>
                <list type="gloss">
                    <label>1909</label>
                    <item>Walter G. Mead, Mitchell &amp; Huckelberry Building, Salem,
                        Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1914</label>
                    <item>George W. Henley, 100 1/2 South College Avenue, Bloomington,
                        Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1919</label>
                    <item>Marshall Williams, 2845 North Pennsylvania St., Indianapolis,
                        Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1924</label>
                    <item>Ray C. Thomas, 504 Broadway, Gary, Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1929</label>
                    <item>John E. Fell, Armstrong-Landon Building, Kokomo, Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1934 </label>
                    <item>Philip E. Byron, First National Bank Building, Elkhart, Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1939</label>
                    <item>Robert F. McCrea, 700 S. Jordan, Bloomington, Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1949</label>
                    <item>Robert E. Gates, The Farmers Loan and Trust Company Building, Columbia
                        City, Indiana.</item>
                    <label>1954</label>
                    <item>Joseph Christoff, 617 Gettle Building, Fort Wayne, Indiana.</item>


                </list>

            </div>



            <div type="editorialMaterial">
                <head>Law Alumni President Extends Greetings</head>
                <p>FELLOW ALUMNI:</p>
                <p>We want you to meet our new baby, christened The I-Witness and launched with
                    great hope that it will tie us closer together, give us more news of each other,
                    increase our membership, help with our scholarship, placement, and recruitment
                    programs, and serve Indiana University better.</p>
                <p>While it will be published with the help of students, its primary purpose is for
                    the graduates and for the Alumni Association.</p>
                <p>We hope you will enjoy reading it, and that you will help by sending in news
                    items about our lawyers in your community.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Sincerly,</salute>
                    <signed>W. Dan Bretz, President</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head>BAR RESULTS</head>
                <p>All Indiana University law school graduates who took the Indiana bar examination
                    this March passed successfully. Congratulations to the new barristers.</p>

            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head>Prominent <orgName>U. of Chicago</orgName> Law Professor Speaks At Law Journal
                    Banquet</head>
                <p><persName>Karl Llewellyn</persName> delivered a speech on "Your Profession at
                    Home" to the staff their wives, alumni, and other guests on March 21 at the
                        <orgName>Van Orman Hotel</orgName>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Llewellyn</persName> is Professor of Law at the <orgName>University
                        of Chicago</orgName>. His major fields of interest are commercial law and
                    jurisprudence in both of which he excels. He has been a draftsman of various
                    uniform commercial acts and is co-author of The Cheyenne Way, a work basic to
                    any study of primitive law.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Llewellyn</persName> emphasized the intangible benefits
                    accruing to lawyers and discussed the responsibilities of lawyers in non-legal
                    capacities. He illustrated the craftsmanship of attorneys by using an example of
                    how various conflicting interests are resolved in a family situation.</p>
                <p>Approximately ninety persons attended the banquet which is the annual highlight
                    of Journal activities. <persName>Bob Miser</persName> Senior Associate in charge
                    of note topic, research, served as general chairman of the banquet.</p>

            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head>OVER 200 HEAR <persName>HALLECK</persName> SPEAK AT LAW DAY BANQUET, MAY 1 </head>
                <p>The Honorable <persName>Charles A. Halleck</persName>, LL.B. '24, keynoted the
                    annual Law Day sponsored by the Law Club in connection with national
                    commemoration of that day.</p>
                <p>Activities for the "day" included Mr. <persName>Byron Kennedy </persName>'s
                    speech the evening before, the freshman-upper classmen softball game, moot court
                    competition and the banquet at the <orgName> Van Orman-Graham Hotel</orgName>.
                    The banquet featured awards to outstanding students and presentation of the
                    Gavel Award and was highlighted by Representative <persName>Halleck</persName>'s
                    speech.</p>
                <p>Judge <persName> James A. Emmert</persName>, former Indiana Supreme Court Judge,
                    introduced Representative <persName>Halleck</persName>. Representative
                        <persName> Halleck</persName> departed from his prepared speech on "The
                    Problem of Federal Preemption" and delivered instead a more informal address
                    dealing with current political problems and more light-hearted reminiscences of
                    his collegiate days here at Indiana University. Federal
                    preemption was mentioned however, with Representative
                        <persName>Halleck</persName> declaring that courts should find such
                    preemption only when Congress has made its intent to preempt clear, and that
                    Congress has the duty to enact new legislation when it feels the courts have
                    misinterpreted its intent.</p>
                <p>The banquet was attended by about 200 honored guests, faculty members, students,
                    wives and dates. </p>

                <p>As a prelude to Law Day activities, Mr. <persName>Byron C. Kennedy</persName> of
                        <orgName>Rockhill, Vanderveer, Kennedy and Lee</orgName> of
                        <placeName>Warsaw, Indiana</placeName>spoke to students April 30 on specific
                    ethical problems confronting attorneys.</p>
                <p> Mr. <persName>Kennedy</persName> was elected Judge of the Wabash circuit court
                    when he was twenty- seven, and served fifteen years. He has been associated with
                    his present firm since 1956. He is a 1928 graduate of the Indiana Law School,
                    now the Indianapolis Division of the School of Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <head>News Of The Law Journal</head>
                <p>The editorial staff of the Indiana Law Journal for the academic year consisted of
                        <persName>Marvin L. Hackman</persName>, Editor in Chief; <persName>Virgil L.
                        Beeler</persName>, Article and Book Review Editor; and <persName>John
                        Backus</persName>, <persName>James Haramy</persName>, <persName>Richard
                        McIntire</persName>, and <persName>William Stewart</persName>, Note Editors.
                    The student writing staff was composed of three seniors and ten juniors. </p>
                <p>Beginning with the current volume, the Journal will be supported by subscriptions
                    and a subsidy by the University. Its former sponsor, the Indiana State Bar
                    Association, has discontinued its support. A subscription should be sent to the
                    Business Manager, Indiana Law Journal, School of Law, Bloomington, Indiana.</p>

            </div>

            <!--   
-->

            <div type="article">
                <head>INDIANAPOLIS WINS</head>
            
                <figure n="VAA7662-001-1-001">
                    <p>
                        <bibl>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Photographer</resp>
                                <persName>Jerry N. Svetanoff</persName>
                            </respStmt>
                        </bibl>
                    </p>
                    <p><persName>James Fitzpatrick </persName>Argues Before Indiana Appellate Court
                    </p>
                </figure>

                <p>The <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> Division won the annual Law Day Moot Court competition between
                    the <placeName>Bloomington</placeName> and <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> Divisions. The Indiana Appellate Court sat as
                    judges for the occasion.</p>
                <p> This year's problem stemmed from a tort suit against an insurance company in
                    <placeName>Alabama</placeName>. An aunt with no insurable interest took out insurance policies on her
                    two year old niece. The aunt then put arsenic in a coke she served her
                    niece,from which the little girl died. Her father sued the insurance company for
                    neg- ligently issuing a policy to one with no insurable interest, obtaining a
                    judgment for $75,000. The primary issue concerned the applicability of the
                    contract rule of insurable interest in the field of torts. </p>
                <p>The appellants for the insurance company were Messrs. <persName>Fitzpatrick</persName> and <persName>Owens </persName>of
                    the <placeName>Bloomington</placeName> Division. Messrs. <persName>Rhoads</persName> and <persName>DeTrude</persName> of the <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName>
                    Division argued for the appellee father. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head><persName>Harris </persName>lectures Feature Outstanding American And English
                    Law Professors</head>

                <p> Comparative Law was the theme of this year's <persName>Addison C.
                        Harris</persName> Memorial Lectures. The lecture series is made possible
                    through the generosity of Mrs. <persName>Harris</persName> who established the
                    fund in memory of her husband, a prominent practitioner in
                        <placeName>Indiana</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Frederick H. Lawson</persName>, Barrister (Gray's Inn) and Professor of
                    Comparative Law at <orgName>Oxford University</orgName>was the initial speaker;
                    his topic was "The Approach to French Law." Professor <persName>Lawson
                    </persName>is currently Visiting Professor at the <orgName>University of
                        Pensylvania</orgName>.</p>

                <p>"The Approach to German Law" was delivered by <persName>Max
                    Rheinstein</persName>, Max Pam Professor of Comparative Law at the
                        <orgName>University of Chicago</orgName>. He is a member of the
                    International Academy of Comparative Law and the German Society of Comparative
                    Law.</p>
                <p> A "Comparison of Soviet and American Law" was the subject of Professor
                        <persName>Harold J. Berman</persName>, the third speaker in the series. He
                    has been a member of the Research Association, Russian Research Center, Harvard
                    since 1948. Professor <persName>Berman</persName> recently argued a royalty case
                    in the Soviet Union for Sir <persName>Arthur Conan Doyle</persName>'s son, which
                    was dismissed, but which may be appealed next August.</p>
                <p> The last lecture of the series, "The Comparative Method in the Common Law," was
                    delivered by Professor <persName>Ronald H. Graveson</persName>, Barrister
                    (Gray's Inn), and Professor of Law at the <orgName>University of
                        London</orgName>. </p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Graveson</persName>is Dean, Faculty of Law,<orgName> King's
                        College</orgName>, <placeName>London</placeName>. He also serves as Chairman
                    of the United Kingdom National Committee of Comparative Law. Professor
                        <persName>Graveson </persName>is Visiting Professor at Harvard this
                    year.</p>
                <p> The lectures this year were held in the Moot Court Room of the Law Building at
                    <placeName>Bloomington</placeName> and were arranged by a committee composed of the following faculty
                    members: Professors <persName>Clifford</persName>, <persName>Hall</persName> and
                        <persName>Rutledge</persName> of the <placeName>Bloomington</placeName>
                    Division, and Professors <persName>Foust</persName> and
                        <persName>Mandelker</persName> of the <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> Division. Informal
                    receptions in the Common Rooms of the Law Building followed each lecture. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <head>SUMMER EMPLOYMENT </head>
                <p>A number of law firms and corporate legal offices are employing students for the
                    summer between the students' second and third years in law school. This plan
                    enables both the employer and student to evaluate one another and determine
                    whether a post-graduation association would be desirable. While the idea began
                    with larger offices it is now becoming popular with smaller firms as well. </p>

            </div>




            <div type="article">

                <figure n="VAA7662-001-1-002">

                    <head>Professor <persName>F. Reed Dickerson</persName> Meets Seminar</head>
                    <p>
                        <bibl>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Photographer</resp>
                                <persName>Jerry N. Svetanoff</persName>
                            </respStmt>
                        </bibl>
                    </p>


                </figure>


                <p>Mr. <persName>F. Reed Dickerson</persName> was appointed as Professor of Law at
                    the <placeName>Bloomington</placeName> Division last fall. His courses include Legislation, Seminar in
                    Legislation, Seminar in Land Use Controls, and Commercial Law.</p>
                <p> He received his LL.B from <orgName>Harvard</orgName> in 1934. In 1938,he enrolled
                    in <orgName>Columbia</orgName> where he obtained his LL.M.; he received his
                    J.S.D. from the same school in 1950.</p>
                <p>Prof. <persName>Dickerson</persName>'s teaching career began in 1938 as a
                    lecturer at <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>. <orgName>Washington
                        University at St. Louis</orgName> then named him assistant professor. He
                    next moved to the <orgName>University of Pittsburgh</orgName> in the same
                    capacity until 1942. He also lectured at <orgName>American University
                    </orgName>in 1956 and 1958.</p>
                <p>The government obtained his services in 1942 when he served as director of
                    pricing standards for the <orgName>OPA</orgName> until 1947. He served as
                    assistant legal counsel to the <orgName>House of Representatives</orgName> for
                    the next two years. He then became deputy chief and chairman of the commission
                    on codification for the <orgName>Joint Army-Air Force Statutory Revision Group,
                        Department of Defense</orgName>, until 1956. He was assistant to the general
                    counsel and deputy assistant general counsel dealing with codification until
                    1958, when he came to <placeName>Indiana</placeName>, having been in charge of
                    the codification of Titles 10 and 32 of the U.S. Code.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Dickerson</persName> received the distinguished civilian service
                    award from the <orgName>Department of Defense </orgName>in 1957. He is a member
                    of the <orgName>American Law Institute National Legislative
                    Conference</orgName>. Governor <persName>Handley</persName> has recently
                    appointed him as an Indiana Commissioner on Uniform State Laws. Books published
                    by Professor <persName>Dickerson</persName> include Products Liability and the
                    Food Consumer and Legislative Drafting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <head><placeName>Bloomington </placeName>Division Professors Contribute To Written
                    Legal Scholarship</head>


                <p>Distinguished Service Professor <persName>Jerome Hall</persName>'s most recent
                    book is <title level="a">Studies in Jurisprudence and Criminal Theory</title>
                    published by Oceana .This book was the subject of an article by Associate
                    Professor <persName>Gerhard O. W. Meuller</persName>, Director of Comparative
                    Criminal Law Project, <orgName>New York University School of Law</orgName>,
                    printed in 34 Indiana Law Journal at page 206. The <orgName>University of
                        Buffalo</orgName> has published his lectures on "Reason and Reality in
                    Jurisprudence" which were given as its Mitchell Lecture Series. Professor
                        <persName>Hall</persName>'s debates at <orgName>Harvard</orgName> on "Mental
                    Disease and Criminal Responsibility" appear in 33 Indiana Law Journal 212. The
                    North Dakota Law Review of October, 1958 carries his article <title level="a">A
                        Law Teacher's Tour Around the World."</title></p>

                <p>Professor <persName>Ivan Rutledge</persName> 's book review appears in 34 Indiana
                    Law Journalat page 138. His review was of <title level="m">Studies in
                        Jurisprudence: V. Free Man Versus His Government</title>, edited by Arthur
                    L. Harding.</p>

                <p> Professor <persName>F. Reed Dickerson</persName> has an article soon to appear
                    in the Rutgers Law Review on <title level="a">"Group Interests in the Field of
                        Food Law</title>." Volume 44of the ABA Journal contains his <title level="a"
                        >"Legislative Drafting: American and British Practices Compared"</title>.
                    The same article is to be printed by the Cambridge Law Journal. </p>

                <p> Assistant Professor <persName>Maurice Kirk</persName> has completed his <title
                        level="m">Second Report to the Governor and General Assembly of Indiana on
                        the Codification of the Indiana Common School Laws,</title> which was
                    published in November, 1958. </p>

                <p>Professor <persName>Ralph Fuchs</persName>' address to the Association of
                    American Law Schools,The Proposed New Code of Administrative Procedure has been
                    printed by the Ohio State Law Journal in volume 19, page 423.</p>

                <p>Professor <persName>John Bauman</persName>'s article submitted to Columbia
                    University toward his doctorate has been printed in 33 Indiana Law Journal 467.
                    His work is<title level="a">A Rationale of Summary Judgment</title>
                </p>

                <p> Associate Professor <persName>W. Howard Mann</persName>'s book review of <title
                        level="m">Essays on Constitutional Law</title> has been published in the
                    Journal of Legal Education.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head><persName>Rutledge</persName> Receives Gavel Award At Law Day Ceremony</head>
                <p>Each year the Senior class presents the Gavel Award to the non-student who has
                    made the greatest contribution to the development of that class. Professor
                        <persName> Ivan Rutledge</persName> received that distinction this year.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rutledge</persName> has taught Administrative Law, Antitrust Law,
                    Constitutional Law, Federal Jurisdiction, Trade Regulation, Criminal Law,
                    International Law, Labor Law, Legal Writing, and Trail and Appellate Practice.
                    Professor <persName>Rutledge</persName>'s analytical approach and emphasis on
                    use of legal principles and tools is perhaps his greatest contribution to our
                    class, although his ability to correlate specific problems to their broader
                    perspectives is no less important.</p>
                <p>Previous Gavel Award recipients include <persName>John S. Hastings</persName> in
                    1948 and in the following years, <persName>C. Ben Dutton, Jr.</persName>,
                        <persName>Bernard Gavit</persName>, <persName>Alfred Evens</persName>, Miss
                        <persName>Margaret Greene</persName>, <persName>Jerome Hall</persName>,
                        <persName>Frank E. Horack, Jr.</persName>, <persName>Leon
                    Wallace</persName>, <persName>Herman Krannert</persName>, Miss <persName>Betty
                        LeBus</persName>, and <persName>Austin V. Clifford</persName>.</p>
            </div>


            <div type="article">
                <head><placeName>Bloomington</placeName> Division Offers New Course For Third Year
                    Students </head>
                <p>A course in trial techniques has been added as a part of the Legal Techniques
                    program inaugurated in 1956. The freshman course involves legal research and
                    drafting problems. Second year students have the traditional appellate level
                    moot court problem as well as other problems. This year the project was the
                    drafting of articles of incorporation from a prior partnership in which one
                    partner had deceased. The seniors this year have been assigned problems dealing
                    with pre-trial and trial steps in advocacy. Problems from pleading to fact
                    investigation to cross examination and motions for instructions have been
                    included to help bridge the gap between student education and actual problems
                    encountered.</p>
                <p>The trial tactics program is under the direction of Professor <persName>Austin V.
                        Clifford</persName> who practiced in <placeName>Indiana</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Chicago </placeName>from 1922 to 1942. He served in the Army as a
                    Captain and Major from 1942 until 1946 working with refugee and displaced per-
                    sons' problems. He was with the prosecution in the 9th Army black market cases.
                    Mr. <persName>Clifford</persName> has been a professor since 1946. He is
                    assisted by <persName>Daniel Rotenberg</persName> who was in the Air Force JAG
                    and by <persName>Frederick Franklin</persName> who was in the Attorney General's
                    Honor Recruitment Program for two years, both Teaching Associates. The Legal
                    Techniques program is made possible through the generosity of the
                        <orgName>Inland Container Corporation Foundation, Inc.</orgName>,
                    established by Mr. <persName>Herman C. Krannert</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">

                <head><placeName>Bloomington</placeName>Division Law Club And Fraternities Have Busy
                    Year</head>
                <p>Under the guiding hands of <persName>Andrew Hays</persName>, President;
                        <persName>Chad Songer</persName>, Vice President; <persName>Gene
                        Pride</persName>, Secretary; <persName>Fred Bauer</persName>, Treasurer, and
                        <persName>Bill Salin</persName>, Senior Member at Large, the Law Club of the
                    Bloomington Division presented a varied program of extra curricular activities
                    for the much welcome "free time" of the students.</p>
                <p>A new activity inaugurated this year was the sponsorship of coffee hours at which
                    various persons prominent in the university spoke. Among the speakers was
                        <persName>Herman B Wells</persName>, President of the University. President
                        <persName>Wells</persName> related his experiences as a delegate to the
                        <orgName>United Nations</orgName>. Professor <persName>F. Reed
                        Dickerson</persName> discussed at another meeting "The Role of the Lawyer in
                    the Department of Defense." </p>
                <p>Athletic activities included the undefeated, un-scored on season of the "Pogo
                    Pups" in the Independent League in football. Since the Medical School has moved
                    to Indianapolis the traditional Law-Medic football game at Homecoming time has
                    been discontinued. Intramural champions <orgName>Sigma Nu </orgName>substituted
                    for the Medical School and were trounced by 6-0 on the strength of
                        <persName>Pete Obremskey</persName>'s touchdown.</p>
                <p>The Law-Med boress was also cancelled but the Laws participated in Homecoming by
                    initiating the Law Walk with canes and derbies and were provided a special
                    section in the stadium for students, wives, and dates. The laws also won the
                    Independent League championship in basketball.</p>
                <p>Other fall activities included the traditional stag party at the Policemen's
                    Lodge and the Fall Dance at the <orgName>Van Orman</orgName> Suburban. The
                    Spring Law Dance was held at the <orgName>Sarkes Tarzian</orgName> Ballroom.</p>
                <p>Besides sponsoring the previously noted activities of Law Day, the Law Club
                    promotes the annual freshman-upper classmen softball game which was won this
                    year by the upper classmen.</p>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Phi Delta Phi</head>
                    <p>During the heat of last fall's elections Phi Delta Phi presented as evening
                        speakers Judge <persName>Donald E. Bowen</persName>, who advocated the
                        Republican point of view, and Senator <persName>Matthew E. Welsh</persName>,
                        who countered with the Democratic viewpoint.</p>
                    <p>The monthly informal luncheon program was once again a success and attracted
                        the following speakers: <persName>Wilbur Stevens</persName>, I.U. Backfield
                        Coach; Assistant Professor <persName>James E. Culbertson</persName> of the
                        Speech Department; Roy Harris, Resident Composer in the School of Music;
                        Assistant Professor <persName>John T. Liell</persName> of the Sociology
                        Department; Associate Professor <persName>Fred Witney </persName>of the
                        Department of Economics; and <persName>Wardell B. Pomeroy</persName>,
                        Research Associate, and Instructor in the Institute for Sex Research.</p>
                    <p>The Spring Banquet, featured Mr. <persName>Roger Branigin</persName>,
                        prominent Indiana lawyer and politician, as speaker. The rush smoker held in
                        the Faculty Lounge resulted in a pledge class of 45 persons.</p>
                    <p>Officers for the second semester are <persName>Max Hobbs</persName>,
                        Magister; <persName>Jerry Newman</persName>, Exchequer; <persName>Philip
                            Siegel</persName>, Clerk; and <persName>Jim Droege</persName>,
                        Historian.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Delta Theta Phi</head>
                    <p>Formal initiation of 23 pledges occured on December 3, 1958. This was
                        followed by a rush smoker on March 3, 1959, as a result of which 20 men were
                        pledged. An informal "Pseudo Ski Party" in honor of the pledge class was
                        held at the Policeman's Lodge on March 14 to which wives and dates were also
                        invited.</p>
                    <p>Future plans include a post final exam celebration and a softball game if Phi
                        Delta Phi accepts the challenge offered. Plans are also underway to
                        inaugurate an annual formal initiation banquet.</p>
                    <p>This year's activities were supervised by <persName>John Cutshaw</persName>,
                        Dean; <persName>Ted Miller</persName>, Vice-Dean; <persName>Jack
                            O'Drobinak</persName>, Tribune; <persName>Gene Pride</persName>, Clerk
                        of Rolls; <persName>Phil Brown</persName>, Clerk of Exchequer;
                            <persName>Jerry Hyland</persName>, Master of Ritual; and
                            <persName>George Rich</persName>, Bailiff.</p>
                </div>

            </div>

            <div type="article">

                <head><placeName>Chicago</placeName> Area Law School Alumni Hold Luncheon
                    Meetings</head>
                <p>April 29 marked the third luncheon gathering of Indiana University law school
                    alumni living in the <placeName>Chicago</placeName> Area. The meeting was
                    attended by <persName>Frank Jones</persName>, Assistant Alumni Secretary, and
                        <persName>Richard Quaintance</persName>, Assistant Dean of the School of
                    Law.</p>
                <p>Earlier meetings were held on March 18, and last December 30. The December
                    meeting was attended by Dean <persName>Wallace</persName> and several members of
                    the law school faculty.</p>
                <p>Future meetings are being planned. For information contact <persName>Richard S.
                        Rhodes</persName>, '53 at Randolph 6-2545.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="article">

                <head><persName>Virgil Beeler</persName> Wins Phi Delta Phi Scholarship
                    Trophy</head>
                <p>The annual Phi Delta Phi Scholastic Trophy for the senior with highest grades was
                    awarded to Mr. <persName>Virgil Beeler</persName>. <persName>Virgil</persName>
                    finished his undergraduate work at Indiana in the Economics Department in 1953
                    and then spent two years in the U.S. Army, including a tour of duty in Europe.
                    After this he enrolled in Law School, winning Krannert, Willkie and Edwards
                    Scholarships. This year <persName>Virgil</persName> served as Article and Book
                    Review editor for the Indiana Law Journal.</p>
                <p><persName>Virgil</persName>, his wife <persName>Jeanette</persName>, and their
                    two sons plan to move to <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> where he will be
                    associated with the firm of<orgName> Baker and Daniels</orgName>. Warning to
                    golfers- he shoots in the low 80's. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <figure n="VAA7662-001-1-003">
                    <head> Assistant Law Dean Named</head>
                </figure>


                <p><persName>Richard C. Quaintance</persName>, an alumnus of Indiana University and
                    former head of a retail promotion service firm in <placeName>Chicago</placeName>
                    has been named assistant dean of the Indiana University School of Law.</p>
                <p>Since his appointment last September, Dean <persName>Quaintance</persName> has
                    divided his time between developing an active placement service for the benefit
                    of students and alumni, and promoting alumni affairs.</p>
                <p>The new assistant dean received the bachelor of science degree in business
                    administration from Indiana in 1948 and the law degree last June.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <head>News Of <placeName>Bloomington </placeName>Division Faculty Here And
                    There</head>
                <p>Professor <persName>Ralph Fuchs</persName> will be teaching in
                        <placeName>Salzburg, Austria</placeName>, in the Seminar in American
                    Studies. His course in Administrative Law will be of four weeks duration.</p>
                <p>Associate Professor <persName>William Oliver</persName> is going to practice in
                        <placeName>Chicago</placeName> this summer and will be associated with
                        <orgName>Sidley, Austin, Burgess and Smith</orgName>.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Val Nolan Jr.</persName> has returned from his leave of
                    absence which he spent working on a study of the marketability of land titles
                    and pursuing his ornithological studies.</p>
                <p>Assistant Professor <persName>Maurice Kirk </persName>will return to teaching
                    duties this summer after having finished his work on school law
                    codification.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>John Bauman </persName>and Associate Professor
                        <persName>Pratter</persName> are both on sabbatical leaves, Professor
                        <persName>Bauman</persName> for the second semester and Professor
                        <persName>Pratter</persName> for the school year.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Bauman</persName> is Visiting Professor at U.C.L.A. Professor
                        <persName>Pratter</persName> is working on a jurisprudential article and has
                    lectured at <orgName>Columbia University Law School</orgName>.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="article">

                <head>News of <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> Division - Faculty, Students,
                    Alumni</head>


                <p>Dean <persName>Henry B. Witham</persName> was recently elected
                    Secretary-Treasurer of the Indiana Bar Foundation. He has completed a revision
                    of Witham, <title level="m">Selected Cases on Contracts Remedies With References
                        to the Restatement of Contracts</title>.</p>

                <p>Professor <persName>Cleon H. Foust</persName> was appointed by Governor
                        <persName>Harold W. Handley</persName> to the Study Commission on Forensic
                    Sciences. His Bill No. 381, "To Create a State Commission on Forensic Sciences,"
                    was passed in the 1959 state legislature. Professor <persName>Foust</persName>
                    also co-authored an article for the current Indiana State Medical Journal-
                        <title level="j"> "Some Medico-legal Aspects of Blood Extraction."</title>
                    In the April issue of Res Gestae appears his <title level="j">The Lawyer and the
                        New Forensic Science Legislation in Indiana</title>". To be issued in book
                    form is Professor <persName>Foust</persName>'s Symposium on Alcohol and Road
                    Traffic at Indiana University-"<title level="m">The Implied Consent
                    Laws</title>."</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>John S. Grimes </persName>has just received from
                    Bobbs-Merrill the 3rd and 9th Volumes of his revision of <title level="m"
                        >Thompson on Real Property</title> and IIIA was just released. He completed
                    and published biennial supplements to <title level="m">Thompson on Property,
                        Thompson on Wills</title> and <title level="m">Henry's Indiana Probate
                        Law</title>. At present he is completing work on the <title level="m">Law of Surveying
                        and Boundaries</title> based on <title level="m">Clark on Surveying</title>
                    and revision of <title level="m">Thompson, Volume IV</title> is now in
                    process.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Lester B. Orfield</persName> was on sabbatical leave the
                    first semester 1958-59 and did research work in the Scandinavian countries. He
                    also lectured at the <orgName>Universities of Lund and Stockholm</orgName>. He
                    was granted a $1500 award by the <orgName>Social Science Research Commission of
                        New York City</orgName> for a study of health insurance laws of the
                    Scandinavian countries.</p>
                <p>Professor <persName>Ben F. Small</persName> is still flying each Monday to and
                    from <orgName>Washington University at St. Louis, Missouri</orgName>,to teach
                    "Constitutional Law." The assignment was for the past and present semesters. He
                    was named by Indiana's Governor <persName>Handley</persName> as an Indiana
                    Commissioner of Uniform State Laws, and was elected this spring to membership in
                    the <orgName>American Academy of Forensic Sciences</orgName>. He recently
                    completed the 1958 Supplement to Small's <title level="m">Workmen's Compensation
                        Law Of Indiana</title>; Chapter 1 on "Causation" in Moritz &amp;
                    Helberg's book, <title level="m">Trauma and Disease</title>, and <title
                        level="j">"The Heart Problem in Workmen's Compensation,"</title> Journal of
                    the Indiana State Medical Association for February, 1959.</p>

                <p>Professor <persName>R. Bruce Townsend </persName>is currently revising the
                    casebook materials for his course, "Commercial Law," which was added to the
                    curriculum and taught the first semester, 1958-59.</p>

                <p>Associate Professor <persName>Daniel R. Mandelker</persName> will begin his
                    sabbatical leave in September. He has been awarded a Ford Foundation grant which
                    will extend his leave through the Second Semester, 1959-60. He and his family
                    will reside in London, England, where he will undertake a study of the
                    administrative operation of English planning law governing development of land
                    and control of land use.</p>

                <p>Assistant Professor <persName>Charles D. Kelso</persName> is presently on
                    sabbatical leave in <placeName>Miami, Florida</placeName>, <orgName>University
                        of Miami</orgName>, doing research for future publications. He has the
                    following works on the presses: Washington University Law Quarterly,<title
                        level="j"> "The Process of Analyzing a Conflict of Laws Case</title>"; an
                    article as part of a symposium in the Minnesota Law Review, <title level="a"
                        >Uniform Reciprocal Enforcement of Support: 1958 Dimensions</title>," and a
                    book review of the Read-MacDonald Casebook on Legislation in the Journal of
                    Legal Education.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="article">

                <head>Student Activities</head>
                <p>The Law Club at the Indianapolis Division has this year been working on an
                    apprenticeship program for students in that division. The basic purpose of this
                    program is to provide students with employment in law offices or in fields
                    closely related to the law. Through this plan, it is hoped thai students will
                    gain familiarity with the practical problems they will face upon graduation. The
                    Law Club's activities in this field are being handled by a committee under the
                    direction of <persName>Norman Kassenbrock</persName>. The work is being
                    coordinated with the division's present placement service. In the very near
                    future a brochure describing the plan will be circulated to law firms and
                    selected businesses in the Indianapolis area. It is hoped that all of our
                    graduates will feel free to contact the committee or <persName>Dick
                        Bodine</persName>, president of the Law Club, in regard to possibilities of
                    employment or any other suggestions they might have.</p>
                <p>Winners of the <orgName>Merchants National Bank and Trust Co.</orgName>
                    will-drafting contest were <persName>William D. Hall</persName>,
                        <persName>Norman Newman</persName>,<persName>John Skinner</persName>, and
                        <persName>John Rhoads</persName>.</p>
                <p>The Phi Delta Phi senior award was given to <persName>Richard
                    Bodine</persName>.</p>
                <p>The U. S. Law Week Award for the senior making most satisfactory scholastic
                    progress was won by <persName>Fred G. Thelander</persName> .</p>
                <p><persName>Robert C. Wilson </persName>had his note "Insuring Risk Loss Under Land
                    Purchase Contract" printed in the November-December 1958 issue of Res Gestae.
                        <persName>William King</persName> has contributed material from "Use of Mob
                    Violence Statutes as a Remedy in the Protection of Civil Rights" for use in an
                    article for the Race Relations Law Reporter.</p>
                <p>Sigma Delta Kappa sponsored a federal pre-trial conference; <persName>Dale
                        Palmer</persName> served as chairman. Participants were <persName>Erle A.
                        Kightlinger</persName>, <persName>Howard Young</persName>,<persName>Arthur
                        Paine</persName>, <persName>Claud Spilman</persName> and <persName>R.
                        Stanley Lawton</persName>. The success of the conference has led to plans to
                    continue it as a regular program.</p>

            </div>
            <div type="article">
                <head>RECENT I-DIVISION GRADUATES IN POLITICAL, GOVERNMENTAL JOBS</head>
                <p><persName>Robert J. Find</persName> '52 is Executive Secretary to Governor
                        <persName>Harold Handley</persName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Karl Kolger</persName> '57 serves as city attorney in <placeName>Wayne
                        County</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Richard J. Groover </persName>'51 has been appointed as circuit judge
                    for <placeName>Henry County </placeName>by Governor
                    <persName>Handley</persName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Lehman Sadler </persName>'54 is with the <orgName>Indiana Securities
                        Commission</orgName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Robert S. Webb</persName> '48 is chairman of the <orgName>Indiana
                        Public Service Commission</orgName>.</p>
                <p><persName>John C. Vandivier, Jr.</persName>, '56 is Assistant United States
                    Attorney General.</p>
                <p><persName>Russell A. Sorenson</persName> '57 is Special Assistant Attorney
                    General in <placeName>St. Paul, Minn</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Richard M. Gwan</persName> '51 is an Assistant Attorney General for the
                    State of <placeName>Indiana</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName>Richard E. Aikman</persName> '55 is with the Appellate Division of the
                    Internal Revenue.</p>
                <p><persName>Joseph Hadley </persName>'51 is Hearing Judge of the <orgName>Alcohol
                        Beverage Commission</orgName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>George E. Marty</persName> '57 is Public Defender for Marion
                    County.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>John Dillon</persName> '52 is Marion County City Attorney.</p>
                <p>Miss <persName>Joan Caldwell</persName> '57 is counsel for for the <orgName>
                        Metropolitan Planning Commission</orgName>.</p>
                <p><persName>David L. Millen</persName> '55 is Attorney-Examiner for the
                        <orgName>Indiana Public Service Commission</orgName>.</p>
                <p>Serving in the Indiana House of Representatives are <persName>Andrew Jacobs,
                        Jr.</persName> '58 and Miss <persName>Marie T. Lauch </persName>'55. Indiana
                    Senate members include<persName> John Ruckelshaus</persName> '57 and
                        <persName>Ruel Steele </persName>'48.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>David D. Finney </persName>'53 is Marion County Assessor.</p>
                <p>Judges include <persName>Everett N. Lucas</persName> '49, <placeName>Clinton
                        County</placeName>; <persName>Milford Anness</persName> '54
                        <placeName>Fayette County</placeName>; <persName>Austin Childress
                    </persName>'54 <placeName>Owen County</placeName>; <persName>M. Walter
                        Bell</persName> '52 Marion County Superior Court No. 1; <persName>Robert G.
                        Robb</persName> '49, Marion County Superior Court No. 3; <persName>Richard
                        M. Salb</persName> '50, Division No. 1, Criminal Court; <persName>Ernie S.
                        Burke</persName> '52 Municipal Court No. 3;<persName> Charles Daugherty
                    </persName>'53 Municipal Court No. 4; <persName>John C. Christ</persName> '51
                    Municipal Court No. 5; and <persName>Noble R. Pearcy</persName>'51, Municipal
                    Court No. 6.</p>
                <p><persName>Frank E. Russell </persName>'51 is Control Division Manager and
                    Executive Vice President of <orgName>Spickelnier Industries</orgName>.
                        <persName>Frank A. Steldt</persName> '49 is with the patent department of
                        <orgName>Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Co.</orgName> at
                        <placeName>Minneapolis</placeName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Peter Martin Witham</persName> '58 is with the <orgName>army
                        JAG</orgName>, <placeName>Camp Campbell,
                        Kentucky</placeName>.<persName>William R. Pritchard</persName> '58 is
                    Science Department Head of the <orgName>University of Florida,
                        Gainesville</orgName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Paul E. Rawley </persName>'57 is Assistant Trust Officer of
                        <orgName>Merchants Bank and Trust Co.</orgName>
                    <persName>Jack M. Schenck</persName> '55 is in the same department.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Richard M. Huston </persName>'51 is Secretary and General Counsel of
                    the <orgName>Indianapolis Legal Aid</orgName>. His professional staff members
                    are <persName>Leroy Frieherr </persName>'57, <persName>John Hammond</persName>
                    '57, and <persName>Bruce Nelson </persName>'57.</p>

            </div>

            <div type="article">
                <head><placeName>Bloomington</placeName> Division Graduates Accept Varied Positions
                    in Government, Corporations, Private Practice, and Service</head>


                <p>This year's class members have taken a wide variety of jobs in many different
                    locations. For those of you who may be looking for prospective associates, there
                    are still several capable students who have not yet accepted jobs.</p>
                <div type="section">

                    <head>Graduates Entering Government Work</head>
                    <p><persName>Marvin Hackman </persName>will serve as law clerk to
                            Judge<persName>Steckler</persName> of the <orgName>Federal District
                            Court</orgName> sitting in <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName>. His
                        appointment is for a two-year term.</p>
                    <p><persName>James Fitzpatrick</persName> will also serve a two-year term as law
                        clerk. His appointment is with Judge <persName>John S. Hastings</persName>,
                        soon to be Chief Judge of the Court of Appeals for the Seventh Federal
                        Circuit.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="section">
                    <head>Corporations Tap Law Grads</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Jon Bulkley </persName>has accepted a position with the Finance
                        Department of the <orgName>Ford Motor Co.</orgName> and will live in
                            <placeName>Detroit</placeName> following graduation.</p>
                    <p><persName>Andy Hays</persName> will be with the industrial relations staff
                            of<orgName> Kennecott Copper </orgName>at their <placeName>Salt Lake
                            City </placeName>office.</p>
                    <p><persName>John Waggoner</persName> will also be in industrial relations. His
                        job is with the <orgName>Trane Co.</orgName> in <placeName>La Crosse,
                            Wisconsin</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Trust Departments</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Ron Baker</persName> is working in
                            <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName> with the trust department of the
                            <orgName>Merchant's National Bank and Trust</orgName> .</p>
                    <p><persName>Al Weber</persName> will be moving to <placeName>Sarasota,
                            Florida</placeName> in a similar capacity with <orgName>Palmer First
                            National Bank and Trust Co</orgName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>With the University</head>

                    <p><persName>Hilliard Trubitt</persName> is Director of Research for the
                            <orgName>Center for Police Training</orgName> at Indiana University.</p>
                    <p><persName>Barry Jellison</persName> will remain at the Law School as a
                        Teaching Associate with the Legal Techniques program.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head> What? Me Worry?</head>
                    <p>The following men found job hunting easy; they are all going to associated
                        with their fathers: <persName>Fred Bauer</persName>,<persName> Ed
                            Grimm</persName>,<persName> Millard Morrill
                            Morrison</persName>,<persName> John Sweeney</persName>,<persName> Jack
                            Rogers</persName>, <persName>Phil Potts</persName>,<persName> Jordan
                            Lewis</persName>, and <persName>Gene Chipman</persName>.
                            <persName>Spencer Schnaitter </persName>will be associated with
                            <persName>Harold Ford</persName>, his father's associate. His father now
                        serves as judge.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head> With Firms in Large Cities</head>
                    <p><persName>Virgil Beeler</persName> has accepted a job with <orgName>Baker and
                            Daniels</orgName> of <placeName>Indianapolis</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Dick McIntire</persName> will be moving to <placeName>Washington,
                            D.C.</placeName> where he will be associated with <orgName>Covington and
                            Burling</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Terry Dietsch</persName> is returning to
                            <placeName>Evansville</placeName>where he will work with
                            <orgName>Ortmeyer, Bamberger, Ortmeyer and Foreman</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Bob Miser</persName> is associated with the Wall Street firm of
                            <orgName>Cahill, Gordon, Reindel, and Ohl</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Hal Sanford</persName> has accepted a job with <orgName>Nicholson,
                            Nisen and Elliott </orgName>in<placeName> Chicago</placeName> .</p>
                    <p><persName>Phil Smith</persName> will be located in<placeName>
                            Minneapolis</placeName> with <orgName>Merchant and
                        Merchant</orgName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>With Firms in Medium Size Cities</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>George Tripp</persName> has moved to
                            <placeName>Richmond</placeName> where he is associated with
                            <orgName>Griffis, Griffis and Cox</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Verl Miller</persName> is in <placeName>Terre Haute</placeName>
                        with <orgName>Rosenfeld and Wolfe</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Dan Connell</persName> has located in <placeName>South
                            Bend</placeName> where he is associated with <orgName>Voor, Jackson and
                            McMichael</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Ken Fedder</persName> will move back to <placeName>Michigan
                            City</placeName> where he will be associated with his uncle.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Dick Good</persName> will be with Jump, Noel and Lacey in
                            <placeName>Kokomo</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Sam Reed</persName> has accepted a job in<placeName> Muncie
                        </placeName>with <orgName>Bracken, DeFur, Voran and Hanley</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Len Malech</persName> will be associated with <orgName>Henry J.
                            Bendheim</orgName> in <placeName>Englewood, N. J.</placeName></p>
                    <p><persName>Jim Jordan</persName> has accepted a job with <orgName>Archie
                            Lapin</orgName> in <placeName>Muncie</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>In Smaller Towns</head>
                    <p><persName>John Backus</persName> is associated with <persName>Karl L.
                            Chattin</persName> of <placeName>Goshen</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>George Wildman </persName>has moved to
                            <placeName>Shelbyville</placeName> where he is associated with
                            <orgName>Pell and Macthett</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Lyle Strahan </persName>is practicing in <placeName>Montfort,
                            Wisconsin</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Dick Bray</persName> is Prosecuting Attorney in
                            <placeName>Martinsville</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Mac Campbell</persName> is going to
                            <placeName>Winchester</placeName> where he will be associated with
                            <orgName>Mendenhall, Hunter and Stohler</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Bill Garrard</persName> has accepted a job with <orgName>Graham,
                            Rasor, Eschbach and Harris</orgName> of
                        <placeName>Warsaw</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>George Languell</persName> is Prosecuting Attorney in
                            <placeName>Owen County</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Stan Matheny</persName> has affiliated with <persName>H. Harold
                            Soshnick</persName> of <placeName>Shelbyville</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Bill Seese</persName> will be in <placeName>Bluffton</placeName>
                        with <orgName>Galivan and Hamilton</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Marty Weissert </persName>is moving to
                            <placeName>Plymouth</placeName> where he will be employed by
                            <orgName>Stevens and Wampler</orgName>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Bill Salin</persName>will move to
                            <placeName>Kendallville</placeName> where he will be associated with
                            <orgName>Finley</orgName>Wyman.</p>

                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Last of a Vanishing Breed</head>
                    <p>
                        <persName>Doug Owens</persName> is the only senior who is bold enough to
                        hang out his single by himself. He is returning to his home town of
                            <placeName>Pendleton</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Miscellaneous</head>
                    <p><persName>LaMar Worley</persName> is in <placeName>Crown Point</placeName>
                        with the <orgName>Calumet Title Co</orgName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Jack Gunter</persName> has moved to <placeName>Midland, Texas
                        </placeName>where he works for the <orgName>Texas Co</orgName>.</p>

                    <p>
                        <persName>Tom Reeder</persName> will be with <orgName>Lawyers Title
                            Insurance</orgName> at <placeName>Miami, Florida</placeName>.</p>
                    <p><persName>Leonard Tompkins</persName> has accepted a job with the
                            <orgName>State Farm Mutual Insurance Co</orgName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Uncle Sam Takes His Toll</head>
                    <p><persName>Jerry Crowell</persName>, <persName>Bill Andrews</persName>,
                            <persName>Fred Bauer</persName>, <persName>Jack Chevigny</persName>,
                            <persName>Jim Droege</persName>, <persName>Dave Keck</persName>,
                            <persName>Marc Lansky</persName>, <persName>Ralph Martin</persName>,
                            <persName>Al Teagle</persName>, <persName>Conrad Harvey</persName>, and
                            <persName>Bill McCrae</persName>, all have a tour of duty with the armed
                        services on schedule after graduation.</p>
                </div>


            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>